Kuroiwa disappeared.
黑岩不見了
His mom said he left a note and vanished.
他媽媽說他留下紙條後就消失了
Don't tell me he…
他該不會…
Ms. Suenaga?
老師？
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同學
Where are you?
你在哪裡？
I loved your lessons.
我很喜歡上妳的課
I just wanted to say that one last thing.
我只是想在最後跟妳說這些話
Last?
最後？
You have someone you want to see, don't you?
妳有想見的人吧？
You should go.
快去吧
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同學
Why?
為什麼？
Because on the phone you said it would be the last time.
因為你在電話裡說了最後
I came because I was worried you said last.
你說了最後，我很擔心所以來了
I heard you ran away from home, and you seemed off. I thought you'd--
我聽說你離家出走 你聽起來不太對勁，我以為你會…
What are you talking about?
妳在說什麼啊，老師？
I meant it would be the last time I would call you.
我說的最後 意思是最後一次打電話給妳
You told me never to come back.
畢竟妳叫我別再去找妳
And it seems you have a boyfriend.
而且好像也有男朋友了
So that was my way of breaking off.
所以我才下定決心離開
So why did you come?
可是為什麼妳卻來了？
-Why? -I'm okay.
-為什麼？ -我沒事
You can go home.
妳可以回去了
How am I supposed to go home?
這樣叫我怎麼回去啊？
Why are you on a boat anyway?
說起來你為什麼要搭船？
Why are you going to Yamaejima?
你要去山江島做什麼？
To see my dad.
我要去找我爸
Dad lives in Bali,
我爸一直都住在峇里島
so I haven't seen him at all, but he sent letters.
所以我沒見過他，可是他有寄信來
Letters?
信？
He sent a letter to mom telling her he's back in Japan.
他寄信給我媽說他回到日本了
I happened to find it.
剛好被我發現
I want to see him.
我想見他
I felt that if I talked to him,
見面之後跟他談談
something would change.
也許會有什麼改變
And your Mom?
你媽媽呢？
Did you call her?
你有聯絡她嗎？
You haven't?
你沒有嗎？
I'm sure she's worried.
她一定很擔心你
I'll call her then.
那我打給她
No, that's okay.
不用了，沒事
I'll do it myself.
我自己來
SORRY, MOM. I'M GOING TO GO SEE DAD. I'LL COME BACK WHEN I DO.
（媽，對不起，我去見爸爸 見到面就回來）
Do you know where your Dad is?
你知道你父親在哪裡嗎？
No, he didn't write his address.
不知道，信上沒有寫住址
But he mentioned he's building furniture at his friend's shop.
不過他說他在朋友的店做傢俱
-That's it? -Yes.
-就這樣？ -對
And if you don't meet him?
萬一找不到人呢？
Do you think you will?
真的見的到面嗎？
I'll think of something if it comes to it.
找不到再說
-But-- -I'm fine now.
-可是… -我沒事
Thank you.
謝謝
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同學
Maybe go to the visitor's center first.
總之先去導覽所問看看吧
Okay.
好
-Welcome. -Hello.
-你好 -妳好
-First time here? -Yes.
-你們是第一次來嗎？ -是的
-Did you just arrive?
-你們剛到嗎？ -是
Perfect! Today's the first day of our Neptune Festival.
你們來得正好 今天剛好是海神祭的第一天
-The parade should-- -Um…
-遊行隊伍應該… -那個…
Do you know any furniture makers?
妳知道哪裡有在做傢俱嗎？
I'm sorry, I don't know of any.
對不起，我不知道耶
Excuse me, are there any furniture makers around here?
不好意思，這附近有沒有傢俱行？
-You know any furniture makers? -No.
-喂，你知道哪裡有傢俱行嗎？ -不知道
Thank you.
謝謝
Do you know any furniture stores?
你知道哪裡有傢俱行嗎？
I might know a place.
我好像知道有一間
Where?
在哪裡？
Do you know the furniture maker Kosuke Shimazaki?
你認識做傢俱的師傅島崎康介嗎？
I don't.
我不認識
I don't know any Kosuke Shimazaki.
島崎康介，沒聽過
What are we going to do now?
現在怎麼辦啊？
Mr. Shimazaki? You mean Shimayan?
島崎先生？是那個阿島嗎？
You know him?
你認識他嗎？
He makes furniture over at the Kajio Lumberyard.
他在那邊的梶尾木材店做傢俱
-Kajio? -Could you show us where it is?
-梶尾？ -您能告訴我們木材店在哪裡嗎？
Yes, we found it.
找到了
Um, excuse me.
那個，不好意思
Is there a Kosuke Shimazaki here?
請問這裡有沒有一位島崎康介？
He's not here right now.
他現在不在
When will he be back?
他何時會回來？
No idea, he went out to fish so probably not for a while.
不知道，他去海邊釣魚了 應該沒有這麼快回來
I'll wait.
我等他
Who are you?
你是誰？
Akira Kuroiwa.
黑岩晶
I'm Mr. Shimazaki's son.
我是島崎先生的兒子
I see, then maybe I can tell you the truth.
原來如此，那我就跟你說實話吧
He's actually trying to keep a low profile.
其實他現在很低調
What?
什麼？
He's in hiding.
他躲起來了
Loan sharks.
高利貸
So he's avoiding any contact--
所以不太跟別人見面
Um, could we meet him?
請問我們可不可以和他見面？
Maybe when we learn his situation, we could be able to help.
我們能好好瞭解詳情 現在有那種針對過度支付的對策
Okay, I get it.
好，我知道了
I'll tell you the real truth.
那我就說實話吧
-He's in the hospital. -Really?
-他住院了 -真的嗎？
Yeah, in the hospital.
是啊，住院了
He just suddenly collapsed.
上次突然碰地一聲倒下了
Dad?
爸爸？
You're him, right?
你是爸爸吧？
You caught me.
被逮到了
Akira.
阿晶
You're so damn big and strong!
你真大隻，身材好壯！
I can't believe how much you've grown!
想不到才幾年不見就長這麼大了
So strong!
真壯！
-Muscly. -What was that about?
-很結實 -剛才那是怎麼回事？
About loan sharks.
高利貸什麼的
Sorry, it was just so sudden.
對不起，太突然了
I mean, I wasn't ready for this yet.
你來得太突然了，我都沒有心理準備
And Aiko told me not to see you without asking first.
而且愛子也叫我不要擅自見你
It's been 13 years, huh?
已經十三年了，是吧？
And who is this?
那這位是？
Nice to meet you, I'm Hijiri Suenaga.
初次見面，我叫末永聖
Look at you, bringing your girlfriend.
真有你的，馬上就帶女友來了
-She's not. -No, I'm his teacher!
-不是 -不是，我是他的老師！
Technically, I'm his former teacher, and he's my former student.
正確來說我是前班導 他是我以前的學生
It's complicated, but I'm his chaperone.
一言難盡 因為一些原因才陪他來這裡
But
可是
I'm glad he got to meet you.
你們能見到面真是太好了
I'll leave you to the rest.
接下來就拜託你了
I guess I will go catch the return ferry home.
那我差不多該搭船回去了
There aren't any.
現在沒船可搭喔
Excuse me?
是？
It's one trip per day.
一天一班
One?
一班？
Yes, you had to be on the ferry you came on.
是啊，要搭到來的那艘船回去
One second please.
請稍等一下
The next ferry is…
下班船是…
-You can crash with us. -Sunday?
-妳可以住我們家 -星期天？
-Huh? -You don't have a choice.
-嗯？ -除此之外，也沒別的辦法
You two come stay with me tonight.
今天你們兩個就住我家吧
It'll be cramped.
會有點擠
-Son? -Yeah.
-兒子？ -是啊
This is my son Akira and Ms. Hijiri.
他是我兒子阿晶，這位是聖小姐
This is Kajio.
他是梶尾
And his wife Wakako.
這是他太太和香子
-Hi there. -Can we join you for lunch?
-你們好 -可以一起吃午飯嗎？
Of course! Come eat!
當然好啊！來吧！
No, I should go look for some accommodations.
不用了，我要去找看看有沒有旅店
-It's no use, they're all full. -It's the Neptune Festival.
-沒用的，到處都客滿了 -因為正值海神祭
And also people are here for the fishing season.
又是釣魚旺季，島上客人很多
Now come inside!
快進來吧！
-It's a bit messy. -This is my house!
-有點亂 -這是我家喔！
Eat up!
請吃！
Good, you found Shimayan!
好耶，你們找到阿島啦
Mr. Kusunogi, this is Shimayan's son!
楠木先生，這是阿島的兒子喔
What?
什麼？
Welcome home!
歡迎回家！
-Go wash your hands! -Wash your hands!
-去洗手！ -快去洗手！
Kajio is an old fishing buddy.
我跟梶尾原本是認識很久的釣友
I was just being polite inviting him here if he was back in Japan.
我只是出於禮貌說 假如他回到日本，就請他過來
Then he actually came!
結果他就真的來了！
I make furniture here to sell online.
我在這裡做傢俱放到網路上賣
So your son brought his girlfriend to meet you?
所以兒子帶著女友來見你啊？
-She's not. -No, I'm his teacher.
-她不是 -不是，我是他的老師
What?
什麼？
Former teacher, former student.
前班導，前學生
We just ended up here together.
我們只是碰巧一起來
-Mom, we're hungry. -Okay.
-媽媽，我們很餓 -好的
-Could I get your help? -Yes?
-老師，可以幫幫我嗎？ -是
Sorry to ask but the squid needs to be gutted.
抱歉請妳幫忙 可以幫我處理烏賊的內臟嗎？
Um… Gutted?
嗯…處理內臟嗎？
Of course, you're a city girl!
是喔，都市的小姐不會處理呀！
You don't cook for your boyfriend?
妳不會為男友下廚嗎？
I don't have anyone like that.
我沒有男友
Okay, I'll do it.
好，那我來
I can do it.
我來處理吧
-Huh? -You can do it?
-嗯？ -你會嗎？
You're so good.
好厲害
Where'd you learn?
你在哪裡學的？
I helped do it at the boarding house.
我曾在現在寄宿的地方幫忙做過
-Give it back. -No!
-還給我 -我不要！
-It's mine!
-這是我的！ -不要！
Now, now, don't fight.
好啦，不要吵架喔
I can't believe she let you.
想不到她會同意
Your mom never responded to any of my letters.
你媽媽從來不回我的信
So why the sudden change?
為什麼又突然改變主意了？
I didn't tell her I was coming.
我沒告訴媽媽要來
This is the stuff.
這個…
What?
什麼？
Ms. Hijiri told me to tell her,
老師叫我要告訴媽媽
but I tricked her and sent an e-mail to my own account.
我把電郵寄到自己的信箱騙過她了
What are you thinking?
你在想什麼？
If I told her, she'd lose her mind and rush over here.
因為我如果說了 媽媽就會抓狂跑過來
Still.
不過…
You know, whatever.
隨便吧
I've waited 13 years, she can cut me some slack.
我都等了十三年了 就一下子，她應該沒關係吧
This seaweed is really good.
這個海藻真的很好吃
Did he reach out to you?
他聯絡你了嗎？
No.
沒有
I hit all the places he might be, but turned up nothing.
我也找過一輪他可能會去的地方了 可是都沒消息
What about the police?
警察那邊呢？
I called a station, and they'll contact me if there's anything.
我聯絡了警局，他們有消息會通知我
Akira can handle himself, and he could be with someone.
阿晶能照顧好自己 他也可能和其他人在一起
Do you think
你覺得
he's with her?
他是和她在一起嗎？
There's no way to know, I don't have her number.
沒辦法確定，我也沒有她的聯絡號碼
Wait!
等一下！
Hold on.
等一下
Um…
嗯…
This person might know!
這個人應該會知道吧！
Him!
這個人是…
Mr. Kawai?
川合先生？
It's been a long time.
好久不見了
Um?
那個…
It's Kuroiwa.
我是黑岩
I'm Akira Kuroiwa's mother.
我是黑岩晶的母親
I'm sorry for coming to your work.
不好意思，打擾您工作
I hate to ask,
抱歉貿然請教
but would you happen to have Ms. Suenaga's contact information?
您知道末永老師的聯絡方式嗎？
Hijiri's?
聖的？
Ms. Suenaga.
老師
I'm sorry.
真是抱歉
Akira is a troublemaker, isn't he?
阿晶他是個問題學生吧？
Dragging you out here.
還把妳拖到這種地方
Not enough parental discipline.
太沒家教了
No, Aiko is doing her job.
不是，愛子肯定有好好教他吧
He has my bad genetics.
只是因為他有我這沒用父親的基因
Not at all.
沒那回事
He was a very earnest,
他是一個非常認真
and dedicated student.
努力的學生
An excellent learner who listened to my lessons intently.
學習能力很強，很認真聆聽課堂內容
Huh, not like me at all.
哦，跟我完全不像
But he was also awkward,
不過也有些笨拙
like when he wanted something,
明明有追求的目標
he pushed them away instead.
卻把它們推開了
He was hard to grasp.
有些難以捉摸
I'm sure he still is.
現在大概也是吧
Now that sounds like me.
這一點倒是跟我很像
She's not answering.
她沒接
I see.
這樣啊
I will let you know when I get a hold of her.
如果聯絡上聖，我會通知妳
Here's my card. Call me anytime.
這是我的名片，隨時可以打給我
Thank you so much.
多謝你了
I'm so sorry to have disturbed you.
真是抱歉，打擾你了
He's already 18.
他都十八歲了
I probably don't need to worry.
應該是不用我擔心
But maybe he's done something with Ms. Suenaga again.
可是說不定他又和老師發生了什麼事
When it comes to her,
只要一扯到老師
he loses sight of everything.
那孩子總是看不見周遭
I just want to know where he is and if he's safe.
總之我只想確認 他人在哪裡，現在是否平安
That seaweed was good, right?
海藻很好吃吧？
Yeah, it was.
是啊，很好吃
We'll have more.
下次再吃
This is me.
這是我的家
Huh?
嗯？
-Here? -It's mostly my tools.
-這裡？ -大多是我的工具
It's clean inside.
裡面很乾淨
Please come in.
請進吧
You can put your things down anywhere around there.
行李隨便放那邊就可以了
Why did you become a furniture maker?
為什麼爸你會想當傢俱師傅呢？
I started off making chairs,
我開始打工做椅子時
and they said I had talent.
他們說我很有天份
It became fun and I just got hooked.
因為做得很開心就迷上了
Luckily, I got to join a big company.
後來運氣好，進了大公司
That's where I met Aiko.
就在那邊遇到愛子
Where's my charger?
我的充電器呢？
You've got exams this year, right?
今年要考試了吧？
Anything you want to do?
你有想做的事嗎？
I haven't decided yet.
我還沒決定
So you fought over that and ran here.
所以才跟愛子吵架逃到這裡來啦
Aiko's gonna be pissed.
愛子會很生氣喔
Leave me out of it.
我可不管
I'm staying out of it. Got it?
我可不管喔，知道嗎？
-Um. -Why did you divorce?
-那個… -你們為什麼離婚？
Because she fell for someone?
因為媽媽喜歡上別人嗎？
It's complicated.
一言難盡啊
Well, when you fall in love one day
當你有一天墜入愛河
and learn what a relationship is, then maybe I'll tell you.
明白了什麼是男女情感 那時也許我會告訴你
I know already.
我已經知道了啊
I've had my struggles too.
我曾經也很煩惱
And someone I like.
也有喜歡的人
Your teacher?
是老師嗎？
I doubt I'll love anybody as much again.
我覺得自己不會再更喜歡別人了
Not more than her.
除了老師之外
This is so hard to watch.
真是的
You only have one thing on your mind.
你腦袋裡只有三個字
What?
什麼？
Kuroiwa with Hijiri.
“黑岩、聖”
Of course I'm worried.
我當然很擔心啊
Do you think it's something serious?
該不會牽扯進什麼事件了吧？
-Surely not. -Or maybe…
-不會啦 -又或者是…
The two of them ran off together?
他們兩人一起私奔了？
One thing lead to another, and they ran away for love.
一發不可收拾，最後兩人為愛私奔
-No way. -But they have reunited.
-不會吧 -可是他們又重逢了吧？
Which is why his mother can't help but be worried.
因此那位母親才會擔心地坐立不安
You can't underestimate a mother's instincts.
你不能小看母親的直覺
Seeing the level of worry she has, it could be serious.
她會像那樣擔心，想必是很嚴重吧
Hijiri's not that stupid.
聖應該不至於那麼笨
It doesn't matter how smart you are, love hits everyone the same way.
不管多聰明，不分年齡、職業、性別 只要墜入愛河，大家都一樣
It makes you want to be together.
只會一心想要跟對方在一起
Thank you for the charger.
謝謝你借我充電器
I'm going to the store.
我去買個東西
Okay, see you later.
好，等下見
Shopping?
買東西？
Yes, I need a toothbrush and other things.
我去一下而已，我沒有過夜用的物品
-You know where it is? -I've go this.
-妳知道店在哪嗎？ -不用擔心，我有這個？
You should go with her.
阿晶，你帶她去
It gets dark early, so just in case.
天很快就黑了，以防萬一
I'll be fine on my own.
不了，我一個人可以去
That way?
那邊嗎？
I told you.
所以才說一起去啊
Give it.
給我
What's wrong?
你們怎麼了？
We're trying to get to the shopping district.
我們想去商店街
That's pretty far.
蠻遠的喔
You should take my bike.
腳踏車借你們吧
The weather will turn, so just be quick about it.
聽說天氣要變糟了 你們快去快回比較好喔
Alright, it's that way!
好，是那邊！
Hey!
喂！
Rainbow's Chocolate!
彩虹巧克力！
I'm buying it.
我要買這個
Look! There's--
看！那個…
Hey… So sorry.
等一下…很抱歉
Congratulations!
恭喜你們！
YAMAEJIMA BOOTS
（山江島靴子）
It's beautiful.
好漂亮
Find any leads?
有線索嗎？
No, I mean, I asked all my friends from back then,
沒有，我問過認識的朋友
but nobody's been talking to Kuroiwa.
但沒人和黑岩說過話
I had Ebihara ask around, but no luck.
我叫海老原去問其他人，他也不知道
I don't want to apologize.
我不想道歉
-I mean, why should I? -What?
-不應該是我道歉吧？ -什麼？
-You're right. -Now hold on.
-也對 -等一下
She told Kuroiwa where Suenaga was, so he dumped--
就是她告訴黑岩 末永在哪裡，所以他才甩了…
It's fine, I didn't like hiding it from him anyway.
沒關係，我本來也不想隱瞞他
It wasn't fair.
這樣也不公平
There's no fair in love.
戀愛沒有公不公平
Whoever cares more loses.
更喜歡對方的人就輸了
Why fight to lose?
為什麼硬是要打敗仗呢？
Ever since middle school, watching you pissed me off.
妳從國中時就一直是這樣 看了就讓人不爽
That's why you meddled?
所以妳才要插手嗎？
Girls are scary.
女人好恐怖
I'm saying it's a waste.
妳這樣太可惜了
Kuroiwa probably disappeared to go after Suenaga.
現在黑岩八成是人間蒸發 去追末永了
Just realize you can't beat her already.
妳差不多該承認自己沒有勝算了
She's the one who can't win, he's her student!
沒勝算的人是她，他是她的學生！
Society won't let them.
社會不會允許的
They don't have a future.
他們兩人不會有未來
You took pictures like that before.
你之前也曾像這樣拍過照片呢
This is my favorite time of day.
我最喜歡這個時間
No matter how bad a day I'm having,
無論我當天過得有多糟糕
it all just melts away.
全部都會融化消失
You love sunsets,
你喜歡夕陽
you can gut a squid,
會處理烏賊內臟
you're good with kids,
很會陪孩子們玩
and you like these.
還喜歡這些
I never knew.
我都不知道
I know a lot about you.
我很瞭解妳喔
Sure you do.
真敢講呢
I feel like I do.
我覺得我懂妳
Back when you were my teacher,
以前妳當班導的時候也是
you tried so hard to act like one.
雖然很努力擺出老師的樣子
Welcome rain on a spring night.
《春夜喜雨》
The good rain knows its season.
好雨知時節
Even though you weren't really confident.
其實對自己很沒自信吧
I don't think you were the only one to think that.
不只是你一個人這麼覺得喔
But now you're confident,
可是現在妳已經有了自信
and you're having fun teaching.
而且做老師做得很快樂
At my previous school, I had an incident with a student.
我在之前的學校跟學生之間出了問題
For betraying all of you,
背叛大家的信任
I'm truly sorry.
實在非常抱歉
You don't know me at all.
你果然完全不瞭解
I told my school
我和我的學校
everything that happened with you.
說出了我們的事
Why?
為什麼？
I wonder why.
為什麼呢？
I didn't think I could hide it for one,
我覺得這件事無法隱瞞到底
and I also didn't think I could be a teacher that way.
也覺得這樣下去沒資格當老師
So they took me out of the classroom.
所以現在被調離副班導的職位
I don't know what will happen.
不知道以後會怎麼樣
But I plan to stop running away.
但是我不打算逃避
I love my current school,
我喜歡現在的學校
and my students.
和我的學生
That all remains true.
這份心意是真實的
I promise to protect you from now on.
我會守護妳的
I'll drop out of school and find a job, then we can go anywhere--
我會休學去找工作 我們去哪裡都行…
Hold on.
等一下
You're dropping out?
找工作？
And college?
大學呢？
I'm not going because it doesn't matter.
我不去了，因為根本無所謂
As long as I have you…
我只要有妳在就好
Let's go back.
回去吧
Your dad's waiting.
你父親還在等我們
SHOTARO
（勝太郎來電）
Leave a message after…
之後請留言…
So many sweet potatoes.
這麼多番薯
I went ahead and took a bath.
我先洗好澡了
This is from Mr. Kajio.
梶尾先生拿來的
What is this?
這是什麼？
Huh?
嗯？
Idiot.
笨蛋
What're you imagining?
你在亂想什麼？
We sleep here, she sleeps upstairs.
我跟你睡這裡，老師睡樓上
Of course.
也對
Idiot.
笨蛋
I promise to protect you from now on.
我會守護妳的
I'll drop out of school and find a job.
我會休學去找工作
You're dropping out?
找工作？
And college?
大學呢？
Thank you so much for your hospitality today.
今天真的很感謝你的熱情招待
It's nothing, thanks for all your help.
哪裡，抱歉，還讓妳幫忙
I didn't do much.
我什麼也沒做
And thank you for the charger.
還有謝謝你的充電器
FROM SHOTARO: ONE TEXT, FIVE MISSED CALLS
（勝太郎，一則新訊息 勝太郎，五通未接來電）
URGENT! PLEASE CALL ME!
（緊急！請與我聯絡！）
-Hijiri? -Sorry, just saw your calls.
-聖？ -抱歉，我現在才看到你的來電
Where are you now?
妳現在人在哪？
Are you alone?
有跟誰在一起嗎？
Why do you ask?
為什麼這麼問？
Kuroiwa's mother came to me.
黑岩的母親來找我
What?
什麼？
She said he ran away from home.
她說兒子離家出走，音訊全無
She came to me worried.
擔心地跑來找我
She thinks he's with you.
她懷疑他是不是跟妳在一起
No…
不是…
He said he messaged--
黑岩說他有傳訊息…
You're with him?
你們在一起嗎？
You are.
看來在一起啊
I don't know how to explain.
我不知道該從哪裡解釋起
Um, Kuroiwa called me.
那個，我接到黑岩的電話
He seemed off, so I went after him, then the ship left.
他聽起來不太對勁 我慌忙追上他後，船卻開了
We're with his father.
我們現在和他父親一起
But we haven't done anything to worry about.
可是我們完全沒做需要擔心的事
Do you get it?
妳知道自己在做什麼嗎？
Do you know what kind of commotion you're causing?
妳知道現在引起多大的風波嗎？
I tried to come home today.
我本來今天就要回去
This could be a crime!
這可是犯罪啊！
-I wasn't done talking. -You need to calm down.
-幹嘛？我還沒說完 -你給我冷靜點
Ms. Suenaga, Dad said to give this to you.
老師，爸說這個給妳
What?
什麼？
You lied about contacting your mother?
你通知母親的事是騙我的嗎？
-What? -Did you lie about it?
-什麼？ -那是騙我的嗎？
I thought she might stop me from seeing my dad.
因為說了，她可能就不讓我見爸爸了
But how?
但妳怎麼會知道？
I need to talk to your father.
我去跟你父親談談
Wait.
等一下
I just came along to see that you made it because I was worried.
我只是因為擔心你，只是陪你過來
That's all. I can't have people get the wrong idea.
就這樣而已，如果被誤解我會很困擾
I'll have him call her so she won't be worried.
我會請他聯絡你母親，讓她別擔心
Wait, where are you going?
等一下，妳要去哪？
I checked again and found a hotel with available rooms.
我又去問了一次，有一間旅店有空房
Right now?
現在嗎？
I don't think we should be spending the night together in the same place.
我覺得我們在同一個地方過夜不太好
Then I'll go home tomorrow.
明天我會直接回去
Who are you calling?
你打算打給誰？
His mother?
給他的母親嗎？
I promised her I would.
我說好會通知她
Is it jealousy?
是嫉妒嗎？
What?
什麼？
Finding out that Hijiri still cares for that boy?
知道了小聖還對那個男孩有感覺？
-No. -Then your pride was hurt--
-不是 -這件事傷害了你的自尊
No, it's not that!
不是…不是那樣！
I'm pissed off he keeps using Hijiri's nurturing instincts
我生氣他在利用聖對人關懷的本能
to confuse and manipulate her.
總是把聖耍得團團轉
I'm also pissed at Hijiri
我也很生氣聖
for falling for it every time, maybe even knowingly!
明明發現了，卻還是選擇飛蛾撲火！
This isn't jealousy.
這不是嫉妒
-I'm just-- -Then just leave it!
-我只是… -那就別管了！
If it's not jealousy,
如果不是嫉妒
and you don't have feelings for Hijiri,
你對小聖已經沒有感情
then just leave it!
那就別管了！
What does it matter?
怎樣都無所謂了吧？
Stop.
不要
I just…
我只是…
This is Kuroiwa.
是，我是黑岩
Hello?
喂？
It's Kawai.
我是川合
Um…
那個…
I managed to reach Hijiri.
我聯絡上聖了
She's with your son.
她跟妳的兒子在一起
TICKET COUNTER
（等待室）
Good night.
晚安
Wake up, ma'am.
客人，醒醒
There's no ferry today.
今天船停航喔
-What? -There's going to be a storm.
-停航？ -遲些會有暴風雨
Do they have a room?
有沒有房間？
They can offer a camp site bungalow if there's no other option.
如果沒地方去 他們可以讓妳住進露營場的小木屋
Yes, please.
好的，麻煩你了
Thanks for the food.
我吃飽了
I promise to protect you from now on.
我會守護妳的
I'll drop out of school and find a job.
我會休學去找工作
Where you headed?
妳要去哪？
-What? -Come on, get in.
-什麼？ -來吧，上車吧
-Are you sure? -Yeah, come on.
-可以嗎？ -上車吧，請上來
Sorry about yesterday.
昨天真的很抱歉
I lost my cool.
我一時衝動
But understand, I don't have feelings for Hijiri--
我希望妳明白 我並不是對聖餘情未了
Jealousy.
嫉妒
I'm not.
我真的不是
No, I'm the one who's jealous.
不，是我在嫉妒
What?
什麼？
Every time you say Hijiri's name,
每次從你的口中聽見小聖的名字
every time you get worked up like yesterday,
或像昨天那樣發怒
I realize I'm jealous.
我就察覺自己在嫉妒
Three years ago with Hijiri,
三年前，你跟小聖
the messy way things ended,
在那種糟糕的情況下分手
it must have hurt you.
你肯定很受傷吧
I can't marry you.
我沒辦法嫁給你
Whose fault is it that we're in this stupid, shameful situation…
是誰造成這麼愚蠢難堪的處境…
I'm sorry.
對不起
There's nothing I can do for you.
我無法幫上你任何的忙
You don't have to.
妳不需要
And still,
可是
I tried to be by your side anyway.
我還是想陪在你身邊
About that overseas position,
上次提到派駐海外的事
I'm still hesitating whether or not to recommend you.
我還在猶豫要不要推薦你
Which is why I'll focus on work.
因此我想專注於工作
Going overseas will help your career.
出國對你的事業很有幫助
I officially nominate Shotaro Kawai to the Singapore position.
我鄭重推薦川合勝太郎派駐新加坡
What?
什麼？
But then
但那樣
what about us?
我們呢？
We're through.
結束吧
Broken up.
分手
Let's end things, Kawai.
做個了結吧，川合
This is our Last Supper.
這是我們最後的晚餐
Even though it's lunch.
雖然是午餐
Thank you!
謝謝！
CAMPING AREA 2.1KM
（露營地，2.1公里）
I took you to the park on a windy day like this before.
我曾在這種強風的日子 帶著你去公園玩
I think you were still about three or four.
你大概只有三、四歲吧
When I told you we should go home because thunder's coming,
我跟你說 “快打雷了，我們回家吧”
you said you'd catch it,
你卻說：“我要抓住閃電
and you're not leaving until you do.
抓不到就不回去”
What?
那是怎樣啊？
I don't remember that.
我不記得了
That stubborn part of you
你那倔強的個性
just like your Mom.
跟你媽一樣
That's why you two probably clash.
因此你們才會起衝突吧
Forget mom.
不要管媽媽了
She doesn't listen.
她什麼都不聽
Especially about Ms. Hijiri.
尤其是跟老師有關的事
NO FERRIES
（渡輪停航）
She won't talk about you either.
她也不跟我說你的事
She keeps treating me like a child.
她總是把我當成小孩子
That's why
所以
I don't expect anything from her.
我對她也沒有期待了
I gave up on her.
我放棄她了
That's why she didn't.
所以她沒有說
Because you're a child, her son.
正因為你是孩子，她的兒子
She protected you.
她才保護你
I was absolutely horrible back then,
以前的我超級混蛋
just the worst.
超糟糕
But she didn't tell you any of that.
愛子什麼都沒告訴你
DANGER! NO ENTRY
（危險！禁止進入）
I was irritable because work wasn't going that well.
因為工作不順利而煩躁不已
So I'd go out and drink.
所以跑去外面喝酒
Whenever you cried, I blamed your mother.
你一哭我就會責怪愛子
I'd yell and shout.
怒吼，大叫
But she held on.
但是她一直在忍耐
She didn't want you to lose a father.
她不希望你沒有父親，這樣太可憐了
So she decided to bottle it in.
所以她一直忍到忍無可忍
I got even more pissed when she told me so.
我聽到她這麼說反而更生氣
I just yelled at her and left.
亂吼一通後就走了
I ran away.
我離開了家裡
So if she then met someone that she felt attracted to,
因此愛子後來遇到了誰，被誰吸引了
even if she had,
就算她喜歡上誰
it didn't matter if we weren't divorced,
不管是有沒有離婚
I'm in no position to say anything.
我都沒資格插嘴
In the end, she took it all
結果她還是咬牙吞下一切
and raised you without saying anything.
默默地養育你
Listen, Akira, if you really love your teacher,
聽著，阿晶，如果你是真心喜歡老師
you have to make the effort to convince your mom.
那就要努力讓你媽理解
Don't run away like me.
別像我這樣逃跑
If you really love Ms. Hijiri,
如果你是真心喜歡老師
become a good man.
就要成為出色的男子漢
Why did he go with her?
他為什麼是跟老師一起去？
Why won't he call me?
為什麼不聯絡我？
Tell me Joffe.
告訴我，喬飛
What's happening to Akira?
阿晶到底怎麼了？
When will he come home?
我要怎麼做他才會回來？
Please someone tell me.
真希望有人能告訴我
Hey! Is Ms. Hijiri here?
喂，老師有來嗎？
She stayed at a hotel last night.
沒有，老師昨天去住旅店了
Apparently, she spent the night at the ferry station.
昨天聽說她因為沒地方住 睡在等待室
What?
什麼？
The ferry was canceled today,
今天船停航了
but she hasn't shown up to the bungalow she reserved!
可是她卻遲遲沒去預訂的小木屋！
-I'll call you back later. -Any luck?
-我再打給你 -怎麼樣？
Welcome back. We haven't found her.
歡迎回家，我們還沒找到她
Where did she go?
她到底去哪裡了？
Ms. Suenaga!
老師！
Somebody.
有人嗎？
Help!
救命啊！
Ms. Suenaga!
老師！
Ms. Suenaga.
老師
Help!
救命啊！
Somebody!
有人嗎！
Somebody, help!
有人嗎？救救我！
Ms. Suenaga!
老師！
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同學
Hold on, I'm coming!
等我，我現在就來！
Are you okay? Can you stand?
沒事吧？站得起來嗎？
I dropped my map.
我弄丟了地圖
Why didn't you call me?
妳為什麼不打給我？
Don't make me worry.
不要讓我這麼擔心
I'm sorry.
對不起
Are you okay?
妳還好嗎？
Yeah.
我沒事
Let's rest there.
去那邊休息吧
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同學
Here.
來
That's alright, I'm okay.
沒關係，我沒事
You must be cold.
你一定很冷吧
Come here.
過來吧
I'm fine here.
在這裡就行了
When the rain dies down,
等雨轉小一點
I'll leave.
我馬上就會出去
Dry off already.
趕快擦一擦
I'm fine.
不用了
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同學
Look,
別看我這樣
I'm a man, you know.
我也是男人啊
So I'm fine here.
所以我在這裡就好了
Besides, the reason this happened
而且會發生這種事情
is all my fault.
都是我害的
Yes, it is.
沒錯
It's your fault!
都是你害的！
It's all your fault.
全部都是你害的
The reason I'm on this island, the reason I'm stuck here,
不管是來這座島，還是困在這裡
it all goes back to you.
都是你造成的
If I never met you,
如果我沒有遇見你
I'd still be working at the school.
我還會留在學校
I could've stayed a teacher.
我還能繼續當老師
But I'm back in hot water,
但現在又惹上麻煩了
so…
所以…
I distanced myself to run away.
我才像逃跑一樣地離開了你
But I don't know anymore,
我不知道該怎麼辦了
what kind of excuse I can give,
我到底該找什麼藉口
what I can blame it on.
該怪罪於什麼原因？
It's so hard.
好痛苦
I'm also…
我也一樣…
Still the same,
仍是一樣
as on that day.
那個時候的我
Back on that beach after the fireworks festival.
那場煙火大會後，那海邊
I'm also still…
我也…
What can I do to forget you?
到底該怎樣才能忘記你？
I love you.
我喜歡黑岩
Yes?
有事嗎？
I'm here to talk about your daughter.
我想跟您談談您女兒的事
-I love Kuroiwa, not as his teacher. -Hijiri!
-我喜歡黑岩，並非以老師的身分 -聖！
What are you doing?
妳到底在做什麼？
But I can't ignore you.
我就是無法丟下妳不管
I'm over you.
我膩了
-Go ahead and cry. -I wouldn't regret it.
-妳可以哭出來 -我不會後悔
Subtitle translation by: Zensho Yamamoto
字幕翻譯：楊易